so it's venus v serena
sister v sister
for the 2017 australian open title
[Music]
thank you players are ready
ready
oh
[Applause]
lovely
interesting to see serena leaning down
the tee there i mean obviously these two
know each other so well not just from
the matches they played but from the
practices as well so trying to bring
something new
to proceedings tonight will be
interesting to watch
[Applause]
of the tournament 189.
devour that serve and it brings up two
break points
oh she picked
[Applause]
[Music]
well that was better than
even patrick's wildest dreams i think
serena could come out and play like that
she set the tone against joe didn't she
when she hit that first return i know
she missed it but she absolutely
cracked it and i think it rocks
opponents worlds when she did that this
time she actually made a couple of them
but that
right out of the top drawer early on
from serena
the first little clinch feast of
determination
wow
15 love
that's an impressive couple of serves
from serena
close to a
average speed on that first serve but
way above on that second and with venus
standing so close to the baseline on
that second seal return you kind of feel
if serena can hit it at about 160 into
the body it's going to be tough for
venus to be aggressive
oh
thirty
let's
[Applause]
sign of the real assets that she brings
this match as well that long reach on
the return and that greater pace of the
backhand than serena's
first ice
force arena
yes
uh
oh
[Music]
cbd of melbourne in the backdrop of rod
laver arena
a little lucky for venus the chance to
break straight back
so
[Music]
[Applause]
it's one game
as well i think just to make sure that
they remain very much engaged early on
here
just a few signs of nurse or serena on
serve
had a game point
to consolidate the break
couldn't convert
[Applause]
again the reach has gone around a couple
of tough situations early on here
venus
[Applause]
she doesn't move it around much does she
venus that second serve it it's often
there and if you just shift over a
little bit give yourself room
there's gonna be a lot of opportunities
for serena to do this
so her first double yet to win a point
when she on that second serve
[Applause]
she's hitting the ball very well from
the back of the core at the moment bodes
well
uh
[Applause]
[Music]
quickly
over striking on the forehand
[Applause]
and a break point for serena
well if the match can stay competitive
it's about playing the big points well
and venus doing a great job in these
last couple of games
clinical finish
wow
frustration
[Music]
that just is a real indicator of where
she is mentally coming into this
so was that frustration because she
slipped over no i think it was
frustration with a neck chord wasn't it
because she obviously had another one in
the previous
on her serve that she didn't handle
particularly well on that one she
couldn't even get too
[Applause]
they put their differences behind them
assist us out here you see that reaction
from serena here
not this one this is the previous point
of course
but she just ripped that return
competitive juices are flowing
advantage
serena williams
so another break point for serena
these players struggling to hold in the
early nervy stages of a final
[Applause]
[Music]
at the best of times let alone break
point down look how low it is look how
low venus had to get to that ball it's a
terrific shot
it's the one thing that she lacks
today that she had back
when she was uh right in her pomp as
well last grand slam she won in 2008 she
was hitting first serves in at 208
kilometers an hour she's lost at like at
her top end she's lost 20 kilometers an
hour off her first serve
and on average she's lost 15 km i mean
that is a huge difference
[Applause]
from serena williams she's come out on
the angry pills already serena williams
look out it could be a wild ride
can she consolidate the break and be the
first player to hold here serving at 2-1
serve out wine i think it's a crucial
one on this juice cypher she's usually
very accurate it didn't really hit one
in that one in the opening game
ah
uh
[Applause]
[Music]
tell you what
it was a surprise to see that she's
bigger off for anna backhand serena but
uh she is really dominating these about
baseline exchanges at the moment just
not finding the finishing shot often
enough
there's the boomer down the
[Applause]
not quite the tape
that we're used to but 170 k's perfect
placement
next
ah
[Applause]
[Music]
second surgery hit of the match was at
160 and i think that's the right sort of
pace for her around there 155 133 she's
going to be in trouble a lot she keeps
throwing those in
[Applause]
venus
it's tough to be as aggressive as she
likes to be on that return in my opinion
when serena's curving out there just
trying to get it back up the middle i
think would be the right place deep as
possible just trying to neutralize that
serve
second double fault for serena
bye
i'm not sure if it's just tightening up
on the bigger points or it does look a
little blustery down
there it's almost difficult to judge it
in the stadium isn't it it was windy
today there's no question about that
take that there's the response
[Applause]
greatest serve in women's tennis
picture perfect
[Applause]
look on the faces of serena's box
[Music]
[Applause]
that's not just tight
that's uh you don't see that every day
off the racket of serena williams no
she's uh
restricted isn't she in terms of her
freedom to do what she normally does out
here with the weight
of history on her shoulders
and she's feeling the full impact of it
right now
seized right up you can just see the
tension
uh
[Applause]
great recognition from venus here just
to be solid off the ground she's not
trying to do too much a couple of very
sort of
averagely paced first serves getting
into the point and then just not doing
anything too dramatic
uh
there is a crackling intensity to these
runnings at the moment
hey
[Applause]
[Music]
she's not really gaining any court
position in these rallies
serena she's been sort of living off the
errors from venus to get the couple of
breaks and right now with venus playing
pretty watertight tennis it's tough to
see the break coming
so venus the first player to hold their
serve
she
[Music]
[Applause]
it's got all the hallmarks of becoming
a very competitive final and serena
battling not just with her sister out
here but with herself massively
and it's been the serve
that is really causing her problems
already
four double faults in the match
yet to hold
[Applause]
[Music]
she's living on the edge at the moment
penis williams
and it is
paying off big time
[Applause]
uh
remaining
15 minutes
[Music]
first one she's made outline
again so important to her because it
obviously widens her attack it widens
space that venus has to defend because
you can see there venus moving to cover
the one down the t which he has hit well
but it's less effective if you can't
find the one out wide
forty years
[Applause]
she's disappointed with a couple of
those shots in this game
third member of any match like this
magnitude momentum was definitely with
her
after the last couple of games
and it takes until the sixth game of the
final for serena to hold a serve
they're all tied up three games a piece
again another indicator of the tightness
that serena's feeling she's not timing
her serve that her now her quickest
serve of the match in fact venus was
serving had served a little bit quicker
up until that point
or she go back to just putting in these
first serves venus
well for her last time
[Applause]
15.
[Music]
[Applause]
second nice of the match for venus
and the second double fault for the
match
well it's not my strongest super volley
and if i'm being entirely honest i'm not
sure
that this is in any textbook apart from
serena's
her issues with the volley last year in
the final against kerber
[Applause]
oh she's cranked up the speed dial
she secured another break and takes a
4-3 lead
listen it's it's a big deal it's a big
deal for her it's a big deal for the
states
and she got a little lucky
in the last
venus uh return game when she missed a
couple of backhands that she's been
making routinely up until that point and
there was a small significant moment in
a match that suddenly the shift can
happen and it did
this crunches that forehand with the
flick of a wrist
some shot
serena must have thought she was at
least gonna see this one or she saw it
she had to afford it
uh
[Applause]
[Music]
superb couple of points here from venus
nice recovery after the disappointment
what happened in the last couple of
games
not easy to shift serena off the
baseline okay
come on
[Applause]
15-30
for the first time in the match serena
has more aces than double faults
five aces to the four double faults
last couple of serena service games of
course venus
what's up
[Music]
so after an early hiccup
serena williams rattles off three
consecutive games
and takes a 5-3 lead in this opening set
yeah the danger now for venus is that
serena's starting to settle and she's
found that sort of out wide on the
outside that's creating some nice
opportunities for her whether it's a
free point or there just the
forehand put away
venus williams serving to stay in the
opening set
love 15.
[Applause]
so
that's the key
[Applause]
well it's a little bit like a
diesel engine which takes a little
longer to warm up isn't it than a than a
normal petrol one but once it starts
finding top gear
it can continue that sort of level of
consistency for a while and serena
looking good now
[Applause]
is going to have to be a absolute best
to even hold on to this service game
well she's landed a few important first
serves in this game
and again she's thinking clearly he
hasn't always executed the plan well but
suddenly starting to put them in again
at 183 she's put a bit more power behind
them
she holds
she's going to force serena to serve for
the opening set
serena leads five games to four
feeling mark she's really yet to
hit fifth gear
i think it's an indicator of the tension
that just not timing it
as well but credit to venus there i
really thought she might end up getting
broken again to finish off that set the
way that serena suddenly looked as
though she was
roaring into life but some terrific
serving has kept this opening set
competitive yeah she won six of seven
points serena williams looked like she
was going to close out that first set by
breaking venus but you're right credit
to venus
and now serena
serving for the opening set
it's the one-two punch
oh
[Music]
[Applause]
so
and it brings up three set points now
for serena
and she seals it with an ace
serena
comes in early wobble to close out the
opening set of his final six games to
four
in 41 minutes
this means everything to both these
players
it certainly does and it's not over yet
although serena's such a great front
runner she has lost a couple of times
here in australia when she's won the
opening set that was uh to anna ivanovic
back in uh when was that 2014 sloane
stevens as well in 2013 so
hope springs eternal
59.
[Applause]
serena's dialed in
kind of the opinion right now if she
does miss her first serve that she's um
actually got to just hit two first
serves because there's no point in just
sort of succumbing and also playing
serena in with just putting those second
serves in in the manner that she has
serena williams hasn't lost a set so far
this tournament the last player to go
all the way through and win the
championship without dropping a set was
maria sharapova in
[Applause]
[Music]
say that again as uh patrick's making
some notes
and it might have said don't hit the
ball as hard as that
up the middle of the court because uh
you've got no chance of getting back
into the court here you can see this off
forward she's on the defense there
really venus but serena hits this right
into the neutral zone but with pace that
you can never get back that's that looks
like a great shot it's actually an easy
shot for somebody of uh venus's caliber
fifteen
so
that's where that served out wide is
just so
important to serena because she hits
that serve
with her eyes shut i think the one down
the t on the outside but
it's not as effective she can't find
them but you can see there venus having
a guard now against the one out wide
there's the one out wide
[Applause]
14 15.
for services
oh
uh
[Applause]
[Music]
so fiance watching on alexis o'hannian
[Applause]
[Music]
suddenly a little untouchable on her
serve
and it's one game all
and again just highlighting the accuracy
difference at times between the two
we've seen venus
salvage that service game at the end of
the first set with some terrific serving
but she's just not as often and as
reliably getting the ball tight to the
lines as serena does and even with
venus's reach unable to get that one
back into play
and that's the biggest problem the
number at the bottom second serves one
two of 11 right now
oh
i love lifting
[Applause]
capitalized on the good length defensive
shot from venus nothing she could do
about that
big problem slamming
for the elder sister
[Music]
so the door is a jar here for serena
williams
will she smash through it and secure the
first break in a second set
holding on by a fingernails here venus
[Applause]
and there's two let-offs for venus
one more to go
[Applause]
digging deep venus williams she saves
three break points
[Applause]
[Music]
terrific shot look at the spin on that
ball as well along with the power that
she put on it because it just kept going
away from serena
she pulls off four consecutive points
[Applause]
[Music]
thank you
[Applause]
[Music]
it's difficult at times for everybody
particularly the two players but
you just want to feel that everything
out there is 100 authentic and certainly
that last game was absolutely
magnificent
venus doing everything here to try and
stop serena creating
individual history
[Applause]
placement down the t
we haven't seen too many thunderbolts
mark
160 k's she's happy with that
just a few precious points of slip by
for venus when they've been there for
her really to capitalize on them
your optimism is so high after a service
game that venus just had as well get
down the other anything i
dodged one there
you know make something happen here
just hasn't really ignited for her
fourteen
thank you
oh
unforced errors creeping into venus's
game
proving costly
she can't believe it as well what a
great defensive shot we've seen a couple
of amazing shots
from out wide on that forehand side
just begging to put away that one
oh that's power tennis at its best
going toe-to-toe from the baseline
[Applause]
tell you what the numbers that are sort
of mounting up now off that forward time
we've seen some terrific shots but that
has got to be eroding the confidence in
it and that's the side the wing that
breaks down a bit doesn't it under
pressure
he'll be a little bit worried as well
he's seen it before
oh
[Applause]
uh
14-15
[Applause]
[Music]
trying to overtake steffi graf's 22 and
claim her 23rd
grand slam singles title here tonight
sometimes uh too little knowledge is uh
dangerous and sometimes too much
knowledge can be dangerous as well to
the way that you play you watch serena
in that last game how many times did she
guess
because she knows which is venus's
favorite serve and she got beaten by the
other ones she's got to be careful to uh
not
let her balance get out of sync too
often on those returns
15.
[Applause]
both are incredibly stubborn with their
court position as well on the return
really would you see them back up and
give themselves a little bit more time
to try and get more balls back into play
[Music]
bit of scrambling
[Applause]
she looks more comfortable up in there
doesn't she venus than serena absolutely
please
uh
daddy
[Music]
let us
14-15
[Applause]
that's why so serena holds
we are leveling three all in this second
set
three games
it's amazing how pivotal the opening set
is in tennis matches as well over the
course of players career only four times
as
either venus or serena come back from
dropping the opening set in their
history
twice each
we've managed it but uh just feel as
though
right now serena just about managing to
get away with
her level of tennis
because she has that opening set in the
bag
[Applause]
like she's loosened up like she's
swinging freely
yeah she doesn't look as though she's
totally buying into billie jean king's
pressure is a privileged motto
clubs it
[Music]
[Applause]
she does do this extraordinarily well
doesn't she this backhand down the line
makes it look easy
[Applause]
oh credit to venus she's responding to
the challenges with some terrific
serving
salvaging situations
[Applause]
that might be the point
the one that sets her on her way to
a historic 23rd major title that is a
terrific bit of defense early on in the
point from serena
break point here for serena williams
so
well it was all or nothing and it came
up nothing
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
advantages she gets a look at another
one here to crack this final wide open
[Applause]
she's none from five break points in
this set
[Applause]
there was nothing fortunate about that
backhand down the line credit to her
that was courageous
just to see where venus goes to there is
a wide open space to the back end serena
sitting on this return down the tee
[Music]
[Applause]
she's confounded everybody here
in australia so
we shouldn't be writing her tennis
obituary just yet in terms of these
major titles she'll decide when and
if
that retirement date comes and given the
caliber of her tennis at times over this
fortnight she'll probably believe that
come the french and woman and she's
still got a chance of going very deep
into those majors
but for now
it's a younger sister in the ascendancy
and that's right up there 186
fastest tonight 191 so just
trying to free up the shoulders
[Applause]
at one point it was four aces and four
double faults now it's ten aces and five
double faults
[Music]
she's a great closure as i say
technically pure the serve in these
pressurized moments there's just
no flaw at all trust it
[Applause]
there's no implicitly sight in tennis
and she can see the finish line now
three seconds
clenus williams serving
to stay
in the decider
crown finding its voice
trying to bring the underdog the veteran
home
thank you
[Applause]
[Music]
let's physicists
oh
[Applause]
good scrambling for serena she's
certainly not banking on herself
needing to serve the sound if she can
find a way to break she will i just hope
venus is alright it looks like she's
just
hurt something there a little bit in her
shoulder
and a bit of discomfort out there at the
moment
and serena
smell victory
[Applause]
trying to force serena
to serve it out here
[Applause]
oh
[Music]
[Applause]
fourteen
shoulder whoop shoulder
[Applause]
[Music]
a little longer but it's serena who'll
be serving for it at 5 4 in the second
so it's 6-4
5-4 serena gets up from her chair and
she will serve for the championship
the daphne ackers memorial trophy
18 years ago serena won her first grand
slam at the u.s open
here she is nearly two decades on
closing in on number 23
[Applause]
[Music]
thank you
15.
[Applause]
oh
ah
[Applause]
take a bow
serena williams sucking in the oxygen
[Applause]
both champions at their stubborn best in
that particular rally
so
ugh
second serve that just oozed class
[Applause]
tension is creeping up
definitely affected her on one of the
shots early in that rally serena didn't
move her feet that's a good sign
attention's there but she managed to get
through it somehow
alright
as the moment arrived here for serena
williams
the adrenaline would be pumping
somewhere in the world steffi graf would
be watching
championship point
for serena williams
thank you
ah
[Applause]
an iconic
what a special moment
[Music]
[Applause]
22 minutes
you